Register of the Delovaia komissiia pomoshchi russkim (Tubabao) (The Active Committee of the Russian-American Union For Aid To Displaced Persons in Tubabao, Samar, Philippine Is.) records
Hoover Institution Archives
Delovaia komissiia pomoshchi russkim (Tubabao) records,
1948-1966
2001C27
Hoover Institution Archives
6 microfilm reels (0.9 linear feet)
Financial records, minutes, lists, correspondence, and printed matter relating to Russians evacuated from China to the Tubabao displaced persons camp in the Philippines in 1949.
Delovaia komissiia pomoshchi russkim (Tubabao)
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Historical Note
Russian-American organization for aid to Russian refugees.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the records of the Delovaia Komissiia Pomoshchi Russkim (Tubabao), that was originally called Delovaia Komissiia Pomoshchi Tubabaovtsam pri Russko-Americanskom Soiuze Pomoshchi i Zashchity Russikih vne SSSR, an organization whose primary purpose was to assist in the emigration to the United States of Russian refugees who were evacuated from Shanghai to Tubabao camp in the Philippines in 1949. The records include a large number of photographs and negatives depicting daily life in the Tubabao camp (accessible only at the Museum of Russian Culture in San Francisco), as well as issues of newspapers published by displaced persons in the camp.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. Photographs and negatives found in boxes 7-8 of the collection were not microfilmed as part of this project and are only available at the Museum of Russian Culture.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Tubabao Camp (Philippines); China.; Philippines.; Refugees.; Russia.; Russians--China.; Russians--Philippines.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Office File, 1948-1966
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, correspondence, financial records, lists, minutes of meetings, scrapbook, newspapers, and subject file, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - General (Reel 1)
    Box/Folder 1: 1
  - Clippings, 1948-1964
    Box/Folder 1: 2. Includes articles about the Tubabao camp, Russian refugees, and the Delovaia Komissiia's activities.
  - Correspondence, 1948-1965
    - General
      Box/Folder 1: 3
    - Ioann, Archbishop of Shanghai, 1952-1953
      Box/Folder 1: 4. Includes proclamations.
    - Lenkoff, Alexander, 1952-1953
      Box/Folder 1: 5
    - Modest, Ieromonakh, 1951-1954
      Box/Folder 1: 6
  - Financial records
    - Accounts receivable book, 1951-1954
      Box/Folder 2: 1
    - Checkbook, 1951-1961 (Reel 2)
      Box/Folder 2: 2
    - Correspondence with debtors, 1951-1958
      Box/Folder 2: 3
    - Financial reports, 1951-1957
      Box/Folder 2: 4
    - IOUs, 1951-1954
      Box/Folder 2: 5
    - Ledger, 1954-1957
      Box/Folder 3: 1
    - Liquidation documents, 1961-1966
      Box/Folder 3: 2
    - List of debtors
      Box/Folder 3: 3
    - Loan requests
      - 1950-1951 (Reel 3)
        Box/Folder 3: 4
      - 1952-1955
        Box/Folder 3: 5
    - Mathew P. Gromoff's financial documents
      Box/Folder 3: 6
    - Receipt book, 1952-1955
      Box/Folder 4: 1
    - Receipts
      - 1950-1958
        Box/Folder 4: 2
      - (hotels and lunches), 1951 (Reel 4)
        Box/Folder 4: 3
    - Saving account statements, 1951-1961
      Box/Folder 4: 4
  - Lists
    - Members of the Delovaia Komissiia Pomoshchi Russkim (Tubabao), 1949-1958
      Box/Folder 4: 5
    - Tubabao refugees, 1951
      Box/Folder 4: 6
  - Minutes of meetings, 1949-1965
    Box/Folder 4: 7
  - Newspaper articles (drafts)
    Box/Folder 5: 1
  - Newspapers published by refugees
    - Dreams come true, 1950 November
      Box/Folder 5: 2
    - Ezhenedel'noe obozrenie, 1949-1950
      Box/Folder 5: 3
    - K novoi zhizni/To New Life, 1951
      Box/Folder 5: 4
    - Nash Golos, 1949
      Box/Folder 5: 5
    - Nash Vestnik/Our Herald, 1951 (Reel 5)
      Box/Folder 5: 6
    - Tubabao znaet, 1949
      Box/Folder 5: 7
  - Scrapbook, 1949-1952
    Box/Folder 5: 8. Includes articles about Tubabao camp.
  - Subject file
    - Concert-balls to benefit Tubabao refugees, 1949-1951
      Box/Folder 6: 1
    - Displaced persons
      Box/Folder 6: 2. Includes bulletins, circulars, memoranda, and other materials.
    - Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations of the United States
      Box/Folder 6: 3
    - International Refugee Organization
      Box/Folder 6: 4. Includes correspondence between Mollie Rule, Director of Operations in Tubabao, and the Delovaia Komissiia.
    - Police Station N1 in Tubabao, sergeants duty-book, 1949-1951 (Reel 6)
      Box/Folder 6: 5
    - Police Station N2 in Tubabao, sergeants duty-book, 1949-1950
      Box/Folder 6: 6
    - Priiut Sv. Tihona Zadonskogo na o. Tubabao
      Box/Folder 6: 7
    - Rossiiskie Emigrantskie Assotsiatsii v Kitae, address to the Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations of the United States, 1952
      Box/Folder 6: 8
    - Russians--Australia
      Box/Folder 6: 9. Mostly correspondence of Savva, Archbishop of Sydney, Australia, and New Zealand. Also includes a draft of a newspaper article by A. S. Lukashkin.
    - Russkii Dom Sviatogo Vladimira
      Box/Folder 6: 10
    - Russko-Amerikanskii soiuz zashchity i pomoshchi russkim vne SSSR (aka Russian-American Union), report, 1952
      Box/Folder 6: 11
    - Miscellany
      Box/Folder 6: 12